[Welcome to this tutorial on building the game, Gnome's Well That Ends Well with Unity.]
[We made this game with the help of the book, Mobile Game Development with Unity by The Secret Lab. ]
[And in this video, we'll walk you through how the game comes together.]
[But before we begin, here's a quick look at the final game.]
[You control a gnome lowered into a well with a rope.]
[Tilt your device to swing, avoid drops, grab the treasure, and climb back to the top to win.]
[So now let's move on to game overview and architecture.]
[The game is built around three main systems.]
[First is the gnome.]
[The gnome is a ragdoll made of physics parts connected by joints. ]
[Next, we have the rope. ]
[The rope is dynamically generated links that can lengthen, or shorten]
[And last, the game manager. Which resets the game, handle scoring and decides win or lose condition]
[So let's down breakdown some of the core mechanics]
[Rope physics. The rope is made of multiple rigidbodies connected by hinge joints]
[At run time, new links are added or removed to extend or shorten the rope]
[Controlled by up and down button]
[For collisions and traps, we used a reusable signal on touch script]
[And any object tag layer, which is the gnome in this project that collides with unity event]
[For traps, it calls GameManager.TrapTouched. For tressure, it calls TressureCollected ]
[For the exit, it calls exit switch ]
[For the scoring and objectives, collecting treasure swaps the gnome sprite]
[So he looks like he's carrying it]
[And reaching the exit while holding treasure triggers a win state]
[For the UI and controls, the gnome moves left and right by reading tilt input]
[The on-screen buttons control the rope length and there's also a pause button]
[Now, let's move on to the assets and folder structure]
[Assets are organized into folders, like sprites, refabs, scripts, and many more]
[First, let's talk about sprites]
[Sprites are the 2D images that represents visual elements in the game]
[In this project, the gnome's body parts. Traps like spikes, treasure icons and background images of the well are all stored as sprites]
[So why is it important?]
[Sprites are important because they are the building block of the gnome's look and feel]
[Without them, everything would just be invisible colliders and physical objects]
[Let's move on to Prefabs]
[Prefabs are saved templates of game objects with components, scripts and properties]
[You can reuse them multiple times in the game]
[So in this project, the gnome, each rope link entraps like spikes or saw blades are Prefabs]
[So why Prefabs are important?]
[Instead of setting up the same trap or rope link from scratch each time, you just drag in the prefab]
[And unity ensures all copies behave the same way]
[Let's move on now to scripts]
[Scripts in unity are c# code files attached to game objects to control the behavior]
[In this project, we have rope scripts which handles generating and extending the rope lengths]
[We have collision scripts which detects when the gnome hits traps or treasure]
[We have the input scripts, which reads tilt controls and button presses]
[And last, we have game manager scripts that keeps track of scoring, restarting or win or lose logic]
[Scripts bring the game to life. So without them, sprites and prefabs would just sit still]
[And now, let's move on to the scenes]
[Scenes are separate levels or screens in unity]
[Each scenes contains it's own collection of game objects, UI, and settings]
[In this project, we have the main scene which is the actual gameplay for gnome rope, traps and treasure exist]
[So why is it important?]
[Because scenes let's you organize the flow of the game]
[So now, after we know the assets and folder structure, let's now move on to building and running]
[To build and run, go to file tab, choose build profile and navigate to android platform]
[Scroll down and choose your device in run device]
[Make sure your android phone is plugged-in to your computer]
[And make sure to enable developers option, USB debugging, install via USB OR USB Tethering]
[Also make sure to download Unity remote on playstore on your android device]
[Once you prepared all of that, we can now move to the next step]
[Make sure your device is plugged-in to the computer and choose your device and click build and run ]
[You have two options but in this video we will just do the unity remove in your device]
[Because you can test the game in the unity editor or with unity remote in your device]
[After that, press the play button and wait until the loading finish and it will run the application automatically]
[And now it works]
[You can now play the game on your android device]
[For the gnome issues and improvements, a few limitations remain]
[Rope physics can feel heavy or unstable]
[The game has only one level and adding more wells would expand replayability]
[Better animations and sound make seem make it more polish]
[Multiplayer or leaderboards could be fun in future upgrades]
[And thats it you know how to build Gnomes well that ends well in Unity]
[From rope physics, traps , treasure up to building the game to your device]
[And you can download this game and try on your own device too]
[Just copy and paste the link that is displayed in this video]
[Thank you for watching and happy game developing]